Showing
a loading indicator is pretty straight forward. So this query object
has another useful property that is is loading.
We can grab that and then here we can say
if is loading we can return a
paragraph and say loading. We can also render a spinner.
Now let's test our application. So back in the browser, refresh, you can
see loading appearing pretty quickly. We can simulate a slow connection
by going to the network tab and applying a
throttling. So here we can simulate a fast 3G connection.
Now let's refresh.
It's going to happen in a second.
Alright, here's loading and then we get the data. So this is the beauty of
react query. We no longer have to declare separate state variables for our
data, error and the loading state. Everything is well taken care of.