So,
here's our current implementation. Now there is a problem here, can you spot it?
Pause the video and think about it for a few seconds.
Here's the answer, we don't have separation of concerns,
because our querying logic has leaked inside our component.
Now to separate these concerns, we should extract the querying logic
into a separate reusable hook. So, back to our project,
let's create a new folder called hooks,
here we add a new file called use
todoes.ts. In this file, first we define
a function called use todoes, and then export
it as a default object. Now,
back to our component, first let's grab this function
and move it to our hook,
now, here we need to import axis, as well as
the todo interface. Now I want to move that interface into this module,
so, back to our component, let's grab it from here
and move it over.
Okay, let's save the changes,
so our code is reformatted, good. Now, in this hook we should
call the query hook and return a query object, so
back to our component, let's clean up our code,
alright, this is where we call the query hook, so let's grab
this piece of code and move it
to our new hook. So here we add a return statement
and return this query object straight away.
Now let's import use query from tanstack slash
react query, good, we are done with this hook, so now
back to our component, on the top, to get todoes,
all we have to do is call use todoes, as simple
as that. Now our component has a single responsibility,
is purely concerned with markup, it doesn't know how the data
should be fetched. If somewhere else we have another component that
requires the list of todoes, in that component we can use our new
hook. So we're done here, the last step is remove
these unnecessary import statements.
So now our component is much simpler and easier to maintain and debug.