similar to
many front end libraries, react query comes with its own dev tool.
It's a powerful tool for debugging and monitoring our queries.
Let me show you how you can install and use it. So here in the terminal, let's
install at tan stack slash react
dash query dash dev tools version 4.28.
Alright good, now let's go to main.tsx.
On the top we should import a component called
react query dev tools from at tan stack slash
react query. Now here we have two items with the same name,
make sure to select the second one with the blue icon.
Because the other one has the wrong namespace, so select this,
so we should import this component from tan stack slash react query
dev tools. Now we should add this to our component tree
after the app component. So react query
dev tools. Okay, so this only goes in our
development build, so later when we build for production,
react query dev tools is not going to be included. Okay, now back in the browser,
so we get this beautiful icon on the corner for
toggling the dev tools. So here's the content of our cache,
currently we have a single item with this key, we can click on this key to see
more details. Up here we have the query details, so we have the key,
the number of observers and the last update.
The number of observers refers to the number of components that are using
this query. So currently we have a single component using this query.
Now if this component is unmounted, meaning if it's removed from the
screen, the observers will be 0 and the query will be inactive.
Inactive queries will eventually get garbage collected and
removed from the cache. We'll talk about that in the next lesson. Now here we have
a bunch of useful actions, we can refetch a query, we can
invalidate it, we'll talk about that later in the section. We have a couple of useful
buttons for triggering the loading and error states.
So if you click on this button, look, this is what the user sees while
they're waiting for the data. Now let's restore this, we can also
trigger an error, so this is what the user sees when something goes
wrong, very useful. Now down below we can see
the data associated with this key, so we have an array of
200 items, here are the first 100 items,
here's the first to do with these properties, very useful.
Now below that we have the query explorer window where we can see
all the properties of our query. This is not something we use that often,
but something that is useful to know is that all our queries have
a default cache time of 300,000 milliseconds,
which is 5 minutes. So if our query has no observers,
it will be inactive and will be garbage collected after 5 minutes.
Of course this is something that we can configure, which I'm going to show you in the next lesson.