Our queries have a few default settings
that work in most situations, but we can always customize them
per query or globally. So let's go to main.tsx
on this line where we create a new query client
we can pass a configuration object, here we set default options
to an object, and in this object we set
queries to an object. Now in this object
we can override the default settings for our queries globally.
Now the first setting we're going to look at is retry which has
the default value of 3, and that means if a query fails
react query will retry 3 more times. Let me show you how this works.
So let's go to use to do's and put an x
here in the url. Now back in the browser let's open up
chrome dev tools and look at the network tab. So look
this is our initial request and right after that we have
3 more retries. Now if the default setting doesn't work for your application
you can always override it. Now let's remove the x from the url
good, back to our main file. The next setting
we're going to look at is cache time which has the default value
of 300,000 milliseconds or 5 minutes.
And that means if a query has no observer meaning
no component is using that query, that query is considered
inactive. Now the result of inactive queries is removed
from the cache after 5 minutes. This is called garbage collection.
I think the default value makes sense for a lot of applications but again
you can always customize this depending on your requirements.
Now the next setting we're going to look at is stale time which specifies
how long the data is considered fresh. Now this has
the default value of 0 which means the moment we get a piece of data
is treated as alt. So the next time we need the same
piece of data, react query will re-fetch fresh data from the backend.
To simulate this, let's change it to 10 seconds, so 10
times 1000, that is 10 seconds.
Now back to the browser, let's open dev tools.
So here we have a green box which means our todos are fresh, but after
10 seconds they'll become stale. There you go. Now
this one that we have here represents the number of observers or components
using this query. Now one of the beautiful things about
react query is that it automatically refreshes stale data under
three situations, when the network is reconnected
or when a component is mounted or when the window is
refocused. Let me show you how this works. So if I open a new tab
here and then come back to this tab, react query will
re-fetch our query, so take a look. Alright,
now we have fresh data. This is a common source of confusion for a lot of people.
They think their application or react query has a bug
because the same query is fetched multiple times, especially with the
default stale time of 0. But this is by design, you can always
disable this feature if you want to. So back to our query client,
here we have three settings for re-fetching data.
We have re-fetch on window focus,
which has the default value of true, we can change it to false. We also
have re-fetch on reconnect, so if the client goes
offline and then comes back online, react query will re-fetch our
queries. Now if you don't like this behavior you can always disable it.
We also have re-fetch on mount, which has the default value of
true, but we can change it to false. If this is set to true, that means
our queries should be fetched when a component mounts for the first time.
I think this setting makes sense for pretty much all applications, but
maybe in your application you don't want this behavior, so you can disable it.
Now, one thing you need to know about re-fetching is that if the data is
stale, react query will attempt to fetch new data from the backend,
while at the same time returning the stale data from the cache to the application.
With this approach we can show the user the cache data immediately,
while also getting the latest data in the background. Once we have the updated
data, react query updates the cache and notifies our component
that new data is available. Our component will then
re-render with fresh data. So this is how we can
overwrite the default settings for our queries. Now, most of the time we don't
really need to change these settings, I think the default values work well for most
cases, the only setting that we often need to customize is
the stale time. And this is dependent on our queries,
some pieces of data get updated less frequently, so we should give them
a higher stale time. So going forward I'm going to remove
all these default settings globally,
instead we're going to configure stale time per query.
So, let's go to our todos hook, this is where we call the
query hook, here we can overwrite all the settings you learn about, so we
can set stale time to 10 seconds.