Alright,
here's an exercise for you. In this project in the react query folder
we have another component called post list. In this
component we are using the state and effect hooks to retrieve
posts from the backend. I want you to use what you have learned in the past
few lessons and create a custom hook for fetching the posts
using react query. Spend a few minutes on this and then come back
see my solution.
Alright, this is pretty straightforward.
Here in the hooks folder we add a new file called
use posts. Next we create a
function with the same name. Here we call use query
and give it an object with two properties, query key
which is posts and query function
and here we should borrow some code from our component
so I'm going to grab these three lines.
Let's move them right here. Now we should
import axis, good. Now we don't care about
setting the posts instead we just want to return response
the data. So this is our query function.
Now we can optionally set stale time
to a value larger than zero, let's say one minute.
So one times sixty times a thousand.
I would like to add a comment like one minute, that's better. Now at
the end we should export our hook.
Now back to our component. We don't need the
state and effect hooks anymore, delete. Instead we should call
use posts. We get a query object, we destructure
it and grab data, error and ease loading
properties. Now here we have a compilation error saying
type is not assignable to type react node. So react
doesn't know how to render this error message. To fix this we go
back to our hook and supply generic type arguments
when calling the query hook. So we should expect to get an
array of posts and an error object in case
something goes wrong. Now here we need to move the post interface
from our component file to this new file.
So let's grab it from here and move it
right here, good. We are done with this hook.
Now back to our component. If you have an error
we should render error.message. Now down here
we don't have posts anymore instead we should work with data.
Now because data can be undefined here we should use optional
chaining. That's all you had to do. Now let's remove
the unused imports on the top.
Finally let's test this to make sure everything is working. So let's go to our app
component and replace to do list with
post list. Back in the browser
here's the list of our posts. Now the last thing we need to add here
is our loading message. So here we can add another
if statement, if it's loading then we return a paragraph and say
loading.