Now
let's see how we can fetch hierarchical or nested resources.
So we want to add a drop down list up here, populated with the list
of users. When we select a user, we should only see the posts
by that user, okay? So here in post list
component, let's add a select element with a couple classes,
form-select, which is one of the bootstrap classes to give this
a nice look and feel, and mb-3 to give it
a bottom margin. Again, this is another utility class in bootstrap
that we covered in the first part of the course. Now, we don't
need the name and id attributes, so delete. Now
because we have multiple elements, we should wrap them inside a fragment.
Good, now,
in a real world application, we should render the users dynamically, but
that's a distraction from what we are focusing on here, so I want to hardcode
a few options for a few users. So let's add an option,
the first one is going to be empty, the second one is going to be user one,
then we add user two and three,
so, here's what we get, it looks good.
Now we need to declare a state variable to keep track of the selected user.
When the selected user changes, we should filter posts by that user.
So, let's use the state hook
to declare a state variable of type number,
and call it user id.
Now, we should handle
the change event of the select element, so
here we set unchange to a function that takes an event object,
and here we set the selected user to event
dot target dot value. Now here we have a compilation error because
our values are strings as you can see here, but our user id
is a number, so we need to parse the value as an integer.
Now we should also set the value prop
to the selected user, so in the next render, the right option gets selected.
Now the last part, filtering, so in this component
we are using the posts hook. Now this hook currently doesn't have any
parameters, but we should add the user id as a parameter so we can filter
posts by that user. So let's pass user id
as an argument here, and then add it as a parameter
to this hook, so this is a number or
undefined, because initially no user is selected. Now,
so far we have had simple keys with a single value, but now that we are
dealing with hierarchical data, we should structure our key a little bit differently.
So we should follow a hierarchical structure that represents
the relationship between our objects. We start with the
top level object, which is users, then we add user id
followed by posts. This is the same pattern we follow
when designing URLs for our APIs. For example, if you want to build
an API for fetching the posts by user, we would
add an endpoint like this, slash users, slash one, which is
the user id followed by posts, right? We are following the same pattern
here. So as we go from left to right, the data gets
more specific. Now here is the thing, the user id is a parameter
for this query. Every time the value of user id changes,
react query will fetch the posts for that user from the backend. So this
is very similar to the dependency array of the effect hook.
Anytime any of the dependencies changes, the effect gets re-executed, right?
We have the same concept here. So anytime the user id changes,
our query will get re-executed. Now the final part is
passing the user id to the backend. Now, json placeholder
supports filtering by query strings, so if you pass something
like user id equals some value, we'll get the posts
for that user. But this is the ugly way of doing this. A nice array
is to pass an object here, here we set params to an object,
and in this object we add all the query string parameters, in this case
user id. As simple as that. Let's test our implementation.
So, back in the browser, initially no user is selected,
so we see all the posts, but if you select a user,
we only see the posts by that user, lovely. Now, let's look
at our cache in dev tools. So currently we have two entries here,
posts by user 2, and posts by all users.
Now the first query is fresh and active with one observer,
but the second query is inactive because here we have no
observers. However, if we change the user
to the first option, the second query becomes active again.
Okay, now I don't like how this key is structured, this null in
the middle looks kind of ugly. If you want to represent all the posts,
it would be nicer to have an array with a single value, that is posts,
but this is very easy to fix. So, back to our project, when setting the key,
we can type an expression and say, if user id is truthy,
the key should be an array with three values, otherwise
it should be an array with posts. Now, back in the browser,
refresh, so initially we have all the posts stored here,
lovely, but if we select a user, now we have
the posts for that user, perfect. Now one last thing before we finish this lesson,
currently we have the posts for user 2 in the cache, so if we select
user 1 or user 3, we will see our loading indicator for a
fraction of a second, take a look. So, user 1,
that was our loading indicator, user 3,
again we saw our loading indicator. However, now that we have the posts
for all these users in our cache, the next time we select the user,
the page gets updated instantly, take a look. So, let's go to
user 2, user 1, beautiful, we don't see a
loading indicator, because the data comes from the cache. This is one of the
benefits of using React query.