Now let me show you how to implement
pagination with react query. Now for this lesson
let's remove filtering by user so we can focus on pagination.
So let's remove this line as well as
our drop down list. Okay, now
our hook expects a user ID, but now we should replace this with
the page number and page size. First we should do
declare a state variable to keep track of the current page.
So use state, we initialize it to one and
call it page.
Now because the page size doesn't change, we don't need a state variable
here, we can declare a local constant. Potentially in the future
we can add a drop down list where the user can select the page size.
In that case, we need a state variable for tracking the page size.
So let's declare a local constant called page
size. Now, we don't want to pass multiple values
to this hook, that is kind of ugly, because potentially in the future
we can have other ways to filter posts, like filtering by user,
page, date and so on. So it would be nicer to
encapsulate all these values inside a query object.
We talked about this concept in the first part of the course, remember?
So let's go to this hook, here we define an interface
called post query. Now
here we add a couple properties, page of type number and
page size of type number as well. Next we change
the parameter of this hook to query
of type post query. Now we should structure our
key a little bit differently. We don't need all this ceremony,
instead we start with our top level object, and then we add
our query. So anytime our query changes, we add query
we'll fetch the posts from the backend, okay? So,
that is simpler, now we should pass the values in this query object to our backend.
So here we need to add two parameters, one is
underline start, that is the index of our starting position,
we can calculate this by getting query.page with subtracted
by one and multiply the result by page
size. The second parameter is underline limit, which we set to
query.page size. Okay, now
back to our component, here we should pass a query object.
Now for clarity, this query object has nothing to do with
react query, it's a common design pattern. A query object is an object
that contains all the values for querying a set of objects, okay?
So here we add page and page size,
now if you go back to the browser, we only see the first
ten to dos. So now we need to add our navigation buttons.
Back to our component, right after our list, we add
a button with two classes, btn and btn-primary.
We call this previous, now this button should
be disabled if you are on the first page.
Now let's handle the click event,
so on click,
we set it to a function, and here we call set page
with page minus one. Now we need a similar button
to go to the next page. Now the next button should be disabled
if you are on the last page, but unfortunately with json placeholder
we cannot tell when we are on the last page, because json placeholder
doesn't give us the total number of records ahead of time.
So we have to leave this out for now, here when the button is clicked we should
increment the page number, the label should be next,
let's see what we get. Alright, so on the first page
the previous button is disabled, beautiful, now these buttons are so
close to our to dos, so let's give them a vertical margin.
So that is my
dash three. Now take a look,
that's better, now the next button is so close to the previous button,
so we should give it a left margin. Now in bootstrap
4 and earlier, we had a utility class called ml that is short
for margin left, but in bootstrap 5 this is changed to ms
that is short for margin start. So instead of left and
right, now we have start and end. So we give it
a margin start of one. That is better,
now if we click next, we go to the next page, but there is a tiny
problem. Look, the screen jumps up and down as we
go in and out of the loading state. Do you see that?
The loading state appears up here and the screen jumps up and down.
We can improve the user experience by keeping the data on the current page
while we are waiting for the new data. When the new data is available
we can seamlessly swap the data for the current page. That is very easy to
do. Back to our query, here we have another property
called keep previous data. If we
set this to true, we get a nicer user experience
as we go to the next page. Look, there is no
jumping up and down, beautiful. So this is how we can implement pagination.
Next I'm going to show you how to work with infinite queries.
...