Now
let me show you how to implement infinite queries in react query.
So we're going to add a button for loading more data.
Now in real world applications we often want to load more data
as the user scrolls down and reaches the bottom of the page.
We'll look at that later in this section. So for now, let's leave out the complexity
around scrolling and focus only on loading more data.
So back to our hook, the first step is replacing
use query with use infinite query.
Let's import it on the top, good. Now when using an infinite
query, we cannot use a state variable to keep
track of the page number, because infinite queries handle pagination
automatically and using a state variable to track the page number
can lead to issues with the cache and data consistency.
So let's remove this line, we should also remove page from
this object and from our
interface. Okay, but how are we going to
calculate the page number? Well, infinite queries have a function
for that. So here we should implement a function called get
next page param. We should set this to a function
with two parameters. The first parameter is last page
which is an array of posts, so last page.
The second parameter is all pages which is a two dimensional array
of posts. So here we have an array and each element in this array
is an array of posts. So this parameter
all pages contains the data for all pages, okay?
Now in this function we should return the next page
number. So if you're on page one we should return two. Now how
can we calculate this? Well, I told you that all pages contains
the data for all pages. So if you're on page one, we have a
single element in this array, right? So we can return
all pages.length plus one as
the next page number. Now at some point we're going to reach
the end of our list. We don't want to increment the page number forever, right?
How can we do that? Well, the implementation varies from one backend to another
with json placeholder, if we ask data for a page that doesn't
exist, we get an empty array. So at some point, last page
is going to be an empty array. So here we can type an expression like
if last page.length is greater than zero
we return all pages.length plus one, otherwise
we return undefined to indicate that we have reached
the end of the list. This is not the ideal way to implement this logic, but that's
the best I can think of with json placeholder. A good API should return
the total number of records ahead of time so we can calculate how many
pages we have and when we'll hit the last page. So this
is how we calculate the next page number. Now when the user clicks
on the load more button, react query calls this function to get the
next page number. Then it will pass the page number
to our query function. So here we should add a parameter and destructure
it to grab the page param. So page param
is a property in the object that react query will pass
to our query function. So now we should replace query.page with
page param. Now as a
best practice we should initialize this to one so we get the data for the first
page. So we're done here, now back to our component,
we're getting a number of errors because we removed our page
variable. First let's remove the previous button.
Now for our next button we should change the label to load
more. Now here we're not going to increment the page number,
instead we should tell react query to fetch the next page. How
do we do that? Very easy. The infinite query that is returned from our hook
has a function called fetch next page.
So down here when the button is clicked
all we have to do is call fetch next page.
At this point react query will call
get next page param to calculate the next page number and then
it will pass it to our query function. Now
we want to disable this button while we're fetching the next page.
To do that we should grab a boolean property here
that is called is fetching, or is fetching
next page. Now here we can say
our button should be disabled if we are fetching
the next page. Okay, now we can make the label
dynamic, so if we are fetching the next page we can return
loading with dot dot dot otherwise load
more. That's nicer. So this is our button,
now we have another error here, because the data object that
we get from this infinite query is no longer an array of posts,
it's an instance of infinite data. In this object
we have a couple of properties, one is page params, the other
is pages, which contains the data for all pages. So
instead of iterating over this to get all posts, we should loop over
the pages and render the data for each page separately.
So, up here, let's write an expression and say
data.pages, we map this, here we map
each page to a container, now we don't want to render a div
in the middle of an unordered list, so here we can use
a react.fragment, now we should import
react on the top, okay, so for each
page we add a fragment, and then within that page
we render the list items, so we map each page,
now we get a post object, so this page, if you hover
over it you can see it's an array of posts, so we get each
post and then map it to a list item, so I'm
going to grab these few lines and paste them
right here. Now let's remove the second expression,
save, so here's the end result, we go to data.pages
and map each page to a react fragment, now because
we're using a map here we should always set the key, now the page
is an array so we cannot use it as a key, so here we need to add
a second parameter, that is our index, and we use that as
the key. Now inside this fragment we map each
page which is an array of posts to a bunch of list items.
Now let's test our implementation, so back in the browser,
here's our button, click, beautiful!
So this is how we can implement infinite queries with React Query.