music playing
So we have covered a range of topics
around queries, now let's see how we can mutate data. So we're
going to add a form for adding a new to do to our list.
So back to our project, here in the react query folder you can find
a component called to do form. I already included this
in the starter project that I gave you at the beginning of the course. Now
in this component we have a very simple form with an input
and a button. Now as you can see we're using the refoke
to get access to the value in this input field. Nothing else is going on here,
very simple. Now we need to add this component along with our to do list
in our app component. So let's go to the app component,
first we add a fragment, inside the fragment
we add a to do form, followed by a
to do list. Okay, now let's see what we
get. So here's what we get, now our form currently doesn't have any
functionality, so the next step is to handle form submission.
So back to our form, here we handle the submit
event, we pass a function that takes an event, now
just like always, first we call prevent default,
to prevent the form from being posted to the server, now you're ready for
mutating data. To do that we should use the mutation hook in
react query. So up here we call use
mutation, this function is defined in tan stack slash
react query, just like the query hook. So we call this hook
and give it an object. Now our queries take a query function
but our mutations take a mutation function. We
set this to a function that takes a to do object of type
to do. Now here we need to get access to the to do interface that we defined
earlier. Currently it's not exported, that is why we cannot access it.
So let's go to use to dos dot yes,
and export this interface up here.
Good, now back to our form, let's import the
to do interface, now we should use axios to
send a post request to the server. So let's import it and call
post, okay we need the url, so let's go back to our hook
and grab this url from here.
We paste it and as a
second argument we pass the to do object that we receive here.
And just like before we call then
to get access to response dot data. Okay,
so we call the mutation hook and get a mutation object,
we can call that add to do. Okay, now
let's add a semicolon here. Now back to our form
submission, here we call add to do dot
mutate, so all mutation objects have a mutate method for mutating
data. When we call this react query will send our data to
the backend using our mutation function.
So here we should pass a to do object, and this to do
object will be the one that will be sent to this mutation function.
Okay, so here we should set a few properties, we should
set the id to 0 because currently we don't have an id, this is generated
on the server. Next we set the title to
ref dot current dot value, this is the value in the input field.
Next we set completed to false,
and user id to, let's hard code the value of 1.
Not the best way to implement this, but for now we just want to focus on
mutating data, not a full flash application. Okay,
now here we have a compilation error because ref dot current
can be null. So here we can use optional chaining,
but now we have a different error saying type undefined
is not assignable to type string. So because we are using optional
chaining here, if the value of this expression is null,
the value of the entire expression will be undefined. So here we should
check if ref dot current exists,
and ref dot current dot value is truthy,
then we'll mutate data. So we want to make sure that
the user types a value in the input field before we send a post request
to the backend. Okay, now let's test our implementation. So, back to
the browser, if we post a form without supplying a value,
nothing happens. We can verify it by opening Chrome DevTools,
here in the network tab, look, we don't have a post request to our backend,
we only have a get request for fetching the to do's. So,
let's type a value and then post the form,
now back to the network tab, we have an additional get request,
this is the result of auto-fetching on window focus, we talked about this earlier
in the section, remember? Now, after that we have a post request,
which is successful, let's inspect it, so this is what we get from the server,
the server generated a to do with the ID of 201.
Now the last step is to add this to our list.
So, back to our mutation, in this object we can add
one or more callbacks, here we have unsuccess which is called if
everything goes well, we also have unerror, when something goes wrong,
this is an opportunity for us to show something like a toast notification,
we also have unsettled which gets called whether the request
is successful or not, okay? Now here we should handle unsuccess,
and set this to a function with one or more parameters,
the first parameter is called data in react query, but we can
call it anything, this is the object that we get from the backend, so we can
call it saved to do. Now look at the type of this parameter,
react query doesn't know the type of this parameter because we didn't specify,
so when sending a post request we should provide a generic type
argument, we say that we're going to send a to do object
to the server, with that if we type a comma here
you can see that the data that we get from the server is a to do object.
Now the second parameter is called variables, the name is a little bit misleading
but this is the input, this is the object that we send to the server,
so we can call that new to do, that is more clear.
Now, in this call back you can do a console.log
and look at the save to do to make sure everything is working,
so back to the browser, let's add a new to do,
and then look at the console tab, so this is the object that we get from the server.
Now here we have two options for updating the list,
the first approach is invalidating
the cache, so we can tell react query that what we have in the cache
is invalid, so then react query will refetch all the data
from the backend, now unfortunately this doesn't work with
json placeholder, because the object that we send to the backend is not really saved,
this is a fake API, so if we
refresh the to do's we'll not see the new to do that we just created,
but let me show you how we can invalidate the cache regardless.
To do that we need to get access to our query client, the query client
that we created at the beginning of this section, here in the main file,
we want to get access to this in our to do form,
to do that we use a different hook called use
query client, this hook is also defined in the
same module, so we call this hook and get our query
client,
now, here in this call back we call query client
that invalidate queries and give it an object,
and this object we set query key to
to do's, this will invalidate all queries whose key
starts with to do, again this doesn't work with json placeholder,
so I'm going to show you a different approach, let me comment this out,
now, what is the second approach, that involves
updating the data in the cache directly,
to do that we call query client that
set query data, as the first argument we pass
our query key which is to do's, and as the second argument
we pass an updater function, now as you can see
the type of this function is unknown because react query doesn't know
what kind of data we want to update, it doesn't know are we updating to do's,
posts or what, so here we need to use a generic type argument
that is to do array, now you can see updater
is a function that takes an array of to do's, so we pass
a function that takes an array of to do's and returns
an array of to do's, so now we should update the data the same way
we update data in react applications in an immutable way,
so we return a new array, first we add the save to do,
and then we spread the existing to do's,
now here we get a compilation error because to do's may be
undefined, to solve this we need to wrap this in parenthesis
and say to do's or an empty array,
let's test our implementation, so back in the browser, let's
add a new to do, there you go.